Welcome back.
This lesson is about using the cube I.D. to create perimeter code.
And what I mean by bare metal code is right and the driver's without use in Cuba makes all the whole
library, meaning access in the registers directly after this lesson.
Go ahead and see how to write a driver's in assembly using cube I.D. as well without using the cube
and makes in the whole library.
And this lesson is going to be in this cube, imex cube, imex cube I.D. cause as well as another course
that I have on bare metal programming in that other cause.
The, um, the development environment we use is the Carl MBK.
So I'm going to include this this lesson in that other course as well.
The reason I'm saying this is that the language I'm going to use in this lesson would be assuming you've
never written bare metal code.
So I'm just going to assume you have no idea.
And I'm going to take you step by step.
If this lesson appears in the bare metal cores, student watch and of course, already know some of
the steps.
So it would sound a bit repetitive to them.
That is why I'm given this warning, because we are going to do it from scratch.
It's going to be from the student of the SDM, Teddy to Cuba mix perspective.
The estimate to Cuba students perspective, because this is not focused on bare metal.
So I'm going to explain some of the things as I do it.
But if you find this lesson in the bare metal, cause this would be like we spoke about this before.
Just bear with me.
And it's better to have it repeated than skipping stuff.
So let's get started.
So to, um, to be able to access the arm, to be able to access, to be able to access the registers,
we need to know the register addresses and the offset how they are arranged and what's the debits in
the wrappers are in the registers represent the registers that uh, 32 bit in size every register.
That is why the arm is a third.
It's one of the reasons why ARM is a 32 bit microprocessor.
So we have to know what bits number one is used for.
It's number two.
It's number three, et cetera.
To find this information out.
We need to download another document.
This time, we're going to download the reference module for the microcontroller chip.
We've already downloaded the data sheet for the, um, the chip, which gave us a quick overview.
We had about one hundred and forty eight pages.
The data sheet gave us the block diagram, um, showing us how the, um, the various peripherals are
connected to the different pass matrix or matrices that the board has.
And this allows us to know what Plock each pair for can have the data sheet.
The reference manual, on the other hand, gives us a detailed explanation of each and every register
India in the microcontroller chip.
So we'll need these documents.
And he has over, I think, over 800 or 1000 pages.
So it's a reference document.
It's not meant to be taken all at once, you know.
Anyway, um, so I'm gonna go to the Web browser and, um, and download it.
So you can just go to Google and type SDM three to four one one reference manual.
I have the four one one board.
That is why this is the the word you may have phones, you, etc..
OK.
This first link says PDAF.
So let's right click this and open this.
OK.
So here we go.
As I said, this has eight hundred and forty four pages.
We simply going to download this.
And I can rename this call.
Oh, call this the reference, my door.
I mean, they all have these long names.
Ref Miyo.
OK.
So once we've downloaded this, we'll go ahead and create a new project and then list out some of the,
um, the, um, the activities or some of the steps we need to take to get this project running.
Okay.
So I'm simply going to minimize this.
And this is our Kubi.
I'm gonna create a new project, file the new look at it for you over here and I'll select SDM 32 to
project.
This one here, not this one.
This one is the M3 to project.
It says Initialise and SDM 32 targets Selecter.
So does the target selector.
Please bear with a resolution for some strange reason.
It's open with, um, with these, um, smaller font.
But this is the same page that we use and, um, in a what Cuba makes to select our board.
So we just come here and select our board, SDM 32 for one one.
So we search over here.
And then over here, we can choose the board we have.
So I just select one or select my nuclear board by what matters.
Yes, the microcontroller.
No, whether it's nuclear or disco is the name of the microcontroller which we searched SDM three to
four one one.
And I'm, like I said, to bear with a small font here.
For some strange reason, Cuba makes opened this way.
And then you are familiar with this page.
All right.
It does the same page from Cuba mix that we select our board.
So we shouldn't be an issue.
So once I've found my board, I'll click on next.
And then once I've selected the board, I'm going to give the project to name.
I'll give this a name.
Let's see.
I'll call this GPI.
You.
QPR, you bare metal.
OK, so next.
And this I kept the same, it's a You Project Cube.
Get the prototype estimated to Cube.
OK.
Target.
I'll leave this the same next.
And then this is the board.
The reference board we selected, this is find firmware package.
You can keep this the way it is.
And then a click finish.
This kind of project is associated with SDM 32 Kubin mixed perspective.
Do you want to open this perspective?
If we want to open this perspective, we can say yes, but we don't need that.
So I'll say it.
No.
Because we're going to do keep Bermejo.
We don't need Cuba, Max.
We don't need the whole library.
We going to go to the datasheet and the reference my no.
Find the registers and manipulate them ourselves.
OK.
So there's the page that shows up.
This page has been opened to allow us to easily, you know, configure our pins.
So if you were to be creating a project using cube I.D., you can still use this method and then use
the whole library by just starting from cube I.D..
This opens.
You select your pins and then you move on.
What this means is you don't always have to start from cube and mix and come to cube to eat.
You can access cube mix from here.
But we don't need all of that.
We said we doing Bamma talks who are close this and then I'll come to see.
There is just what we have here.
It brought the whole library.
We don't need a whole library.
You brought this.
It couldn't help it.
So that's what SD is doing here.
So the system generated the whole library regardless because it assumes 99 percent of the time.
If you get on a project, you need the hardware obstruction layer, which is the whole library.
So we have the whole library here.
But we don't need that.
What are we going to be using as just a single header file?
Which we find in the CMC is okay.
So I'm going to quote the source folder.
This is our project.
This was located right.
Click at New and in our other folder called The Source Our Like This.
And this is just to show that, you know, we have a source folder in all of the project, the project
structure.
You often have your source inside your source, inside your source for.
You have your main Ötzi Fall and the other files you need.
So I have this source photo here.
And then I'm going to come over here inside this source folder.
I'll close this.
This is still our project, GPL.
You underscore Babymetal inside a source.
All right, click add.
New item or or new.
Why am I seeing a new item?
Okay.
New.
And then select followed by here.
Then this fall is going to be main dot c.
And then finish.
Okay.
So now we have our main see here.
And I'm going to include our SDM 32 head of file.
The head of file that gives the register addresses and locations we see include.
Besty M 32, f four.
We're using the F for board x x dot h x.
X means O f four essentially.
And I'm simply going to say int main.
Over here.
And this is void.
I want to just write this and test and see that we build successfully before we go on.
Okay.
And we can put our infinite loop in here.
Open and close.
Right.
So once this is done, we can click here to build.
Let's see what we have learned in all of the whole library drivers.
We can delete them, but we don't need to delete them.
This was just a demo.
But if you don't want to if you don't want this whole library stuff to take space on your firmware,
we don't need any of that here.
They can be deleted.
We're not using them.
You see, we know we don't have as tempted to underscore h e a eldard each.
We don't have it in our projects or we can delete everything related to it.
OK.
So we have no error.
No warning.
Right.
So the setup looks good.
So in this example, what we're going to do is basically togo the LCD on our nuclear board and this
can be in a SDM 32 F4 board at all.
The only difference is that you would have to connect the LTT differently on your particular body if
you are the disco board on disco.
The LCD are connected elsewhere.
But if you want to follow along without changing anything, you may need to connect on X10 or ality
to a port so that you can use the same pin.
The reason I'm saying this is that the nuclear boards elite is connected to P five.
So we're going to be enabling P five as an output pin, using bare metal, using the bare metal method.
If you may call it that.
So, you know, in modern day microcontrollers, before you use any part of the microcontroller in a
module or in your peripheral, you have to enable clock access to that part.
And the reason why we do this is because of something known as the clock gating mechanism.
Microcontrollers from the past long ago, about maybe two decades ago, didn't have this clock Gayton
mechanism.
And what I meant is if you turn on the microcontroller or all the parts sort of consume some power.
Right.
Cos they all have clock access open to them.
So due to the rise of, you know, low power development, finding ways to optimize, you know, power
usage, et cetera.
And we became one of the solutions.
So what this means is by default, the microcontroller has the clock cutoff from the different parts.
If you want to use a particle apart, you enable clock access to just that part two.
If I want to use HTC One, I enable clock access to ADC one without an enabling clock for the other
parts, such as you, art and other peripherals.
So this is what the clock caginess about.
And the bus, the bus of the arm of the microcontroller tells us how the clock lines are connected.
So to start off, let's take a look at the, um, the bus connection of the peripherals.
We said we're going to be dealing with GPI, you port.
So we want to know where port is connected.
If we can find a bus of Port A. Then we know how to enable clock to port A SO to find the bus, we need
to go to the SDM three to four one one datasheet document.
This is different from the reference document.
The datasheet documents is the document with the M with a block diagram.
We need to take a look at the block diagram.
I think I have the data sheet here.
So if you don't have that, you can just go on line, search SDM 32 F for one one datasheet.
And this is the um, is a called data sheet.
Liz, let's see what is written up here.
OK, so this is it.
This is classified as the datasheet when India and the arrangement and the other one is classified as
the.
The reference my notes written here.
Datasheet.
Over here.
So we need to take a look at the block diagram.
So I'm going to scroll down here.
We just posted this one over here.
I'm going to zoom in.
OK.
Well, assuming a bit.
OK, so this diagram here shows us the, um, the buses connecting the various parts of the of the of
the microcontroller.
So there are two buses.
Generally, we have the HP, the APB bus and the HP bus.
HP allows us to allows us for allows faster access.
Basically, you can access a particular part of the microcontroller with fewer clock cycles when using
the HP as compared to the APD.
APB is the legacy buses from the past and the HP is the more recent one.
But they keep both to allow portability.
So over here you see HP over here.
And then we have APB and HP are further divided into HP, one APB one, et cetera.
So to know how a particular component is connected, you just have to trace the arrows, the arrows
connecting it.
And then from the arrow, you know which bus.
So this is GPL, your ports.
If you look at UK ports, we see this arrow connection to G.P.A..
You put a and then connect into this other bus here.
When we look at the name of the bus, the bus is called a HP one bus.
So we know to access GPL, you put it to enable it.
We need to enable it using the HP one meaning there is something in the HP module without allow us to
enable G.P.A..
You put a is the same for ports B, C, D and E, you can trace them.
But if we were to use a different peripherals such as t I am M2 meaning time two, we know that we can
trace and locate it bus from here.
It's connected to the APB, one bus, the APB, one bus gives us access to time or two.
So after knowing this we know GPL, you say it is HP one.
So we can just keep a comment up here, a HP one like this.
OK.
And we said we're dealing with P five.
P A five.
That's.
Well, it is connected.
Right.
So to enable the HP one, we need to go to the data sheet and see what HP what looks like.
So we need to go to data sheets and search HP one and Naples, register the register for enabling HP
one.
I mean, reference manual.
This is the data sheet.
So we need to open the reference manual next.
Does the one that gives us the register information.
So come over here.
That will click this to open.
And there's the reference manual.
This one is bigger.
So there's a trick for dealing with this.
You simply search for what you are looking.
You all do control.
If you open the search box here and then I'm going to search HP one.
And then I hit enter.
And then it's probably here and then.
Oh, hit enter again.
I'm looking for HP one enabler register.
So this one here says RACC, a HP one pair, four o'clock enabler register.
This the one we're dealing with.
So click this.
And when I come here it tells me over here.
It shows the 32 bit register.
And we say 32 bits because we count from zero.
So if you count from zero through thirty one, you end up with 32.
Right.
So over here it says pit zero is GPA you a enable between GPL, you B enable B to GPL, you see a network
cetera.
So let's go to pit zero.
Over here, the bits I explained or that decoded if you want to see it.
So if I scroll down here to go to the part where it tells me BOPE, it's zero like it said in the diagram,
but zero is GPL you enable.
And it says, I Allport a clock and enable set and cleared by software.
And over here it gives a simple Truta table, if you want to call it that.
It says if it is set to zero then I put a clock is disabled.
If it is set to one then I o clock.
When they said to one, then I put a clock.
It is enabled.
So to enable clock four point eight we have to set this over here to one.
So yeah, that is point number one.
So we know what to do here.
So we can, um, we can take note of the we can, um, say
set the register called RACC,
HP one enable register set bitz zero.
Oh see I said it's zero
or Qasi HP one, two, one does what we want to do to enable clock access.
Right.
Next.
So once we do this auction clock access is going to be um is going to be available to keep you put in.
Now we can we can choose whichever pin we want on the port to use for our purpose.
But we said we use MPLX five.
This brings another explanation which regards to the way microcontrollers work.
So any microcontroller at all.
Um, when dealing with GPI, you GPI U stands for general purpose input output.
When dealing with GPA, you there are at least at least at least two registers that any microcontroller
would have, what, eight, eight bits.
Sixteen bits.
Thirty two bits.
There are at least two registers when it comes, when it comes to dealing with GPL.
You and these two registers are the um the direction register and the data register.
These are the at least two, but you would never in modern day microcontrollers, you would find more
than two, but all of them contain this, at least to the direction register is used to set the GPL.
You remember, GPL stands for general purpose, input output.
We use that direction to set the direction, whether we want it to be input or output.
We use that direction to do that.
Direction register.
To do that.
And they, um, the data register, based on whether you choose to set it as input or output, would
either contain the data or would give the data that is to be able to put it out.
Right.
So at least they have these two registers.
So these are the generic names of the registers.
Um, data register and direction register.
So I mentioned.
OK.
So given this fundamental, um, given this, um, fundamental knowledge, microcontroller manufacturers,
um, build upon this to add more options to it.
So I mentioned in GPL you you can have it either as input or output because of the complexity of modern
day microcontrollers.
Our GPI, you pin p five is not simply a GPO.
We can configure p a five also into an s p i o n s p i.
O stands for special purpose input output.
So because we have this other option in this so called Direxion Register, our options are no longer
choose input or output.
There's another option known as alternate function option.
So we can also set it to an alternate function.
And by setting it to an alternate function, we can say we want to use P a five as a U at our x p,
meaning you are to receive Peine or you are to explain or as a plutonium generator in all.
I said that.
So these are these are peripherals such as you at ADC, DHC, the special purpose peripherals, the
base pair for the general purpose is the simple G.P.A. you about all of these peripherals.
They deal with Paines as well.
So you have to configure the pin to be a special purpose being to use it.
So with this, then we access the same, the same direction register.
Right.
So direction register.
However, when you go to the data sheet and the reference my notes or from silicon manufactories, you
wouldn't find the, um, the word direction register.
They've given us this functionality or this registered different names.
If you go to the, um, the data sheet of the Texas instrument.
Um, Tim Forese, one, two, three.
This is still called Director Register.
But, you know, SDM 32.
This is called the Mode Register, cos it makes sense.
You are setting the mood.
So yeah, in other manufactories, I'm sure an B would have a different name for this same register,
but fundamentally they do the same thing.
So this brings us to going to find our more register.
And then, um, and then dealing with it.
So we're going to go back to a work reference my no and find a note register.
And see how the more register or the direction.
Remember when I say mode and direction, I'm using it interchangeably because I gave you the prologue.
I gave it introduction using the word director register.
So you can think of them as the same.
So we go to the, um, the reference manual, find this direction register or more register and see
what we have to do to this register to set out what, a five as an output pin because P five can be
output, it can be input and it can be a special purpose as well.
We have to say we want this pain to be output for this project and we have to find that.
Okay.
So let's go to the, um, the reference model.
I think I still have it open over here, so I'll come back to the top o scroll back to the top control
F to search F here and then I'm going to search mode.
Ah.
And then now hit enter and then it's probably here under GPL your register.
He says g.p or Port Moad registered.
The R stands for register.
That is why it's written mode.
Ah.
So we can click here to read about it.
Okay.
It says GPL you Portmore Register and GPL your GPA you on this uh subscript X mode register.
And it says X stands for a, e and H e all the way to H I should see.
And this means GPA.
You put a puts people C D all the way to H over here like we said or register s 32 bits if they are
not thirty two.
Although the other two bits, not all of them have all.
It's been used, for instance, this one down here.
We don't use the upper upper arm.
Fifteen bits.
Sixteen bits.
They're reserved.
OK.
So this one would register.
And it's it's broken down into mode zero.
Through mode.
Fifteen.
Right.
More to zero.
Takes the first two bit bits.
Zero and bit one more.
Fifteen takes the last two bits to thirty and a bit.
Thirty one.
So let's read about what mod zero is.
One word.
One is what mode two is, et cetera.
Over here it says.
Mode.
Subscript y.
And over here it gives bits zero through one meaning they take one bit.
Um.
Yeah.
And it says Port X configuration Y equals zero through fifteen.
Meaning Y.
Here.
Represent more to zero mode one mode to all the way toward fifteen.
Right.
So he says these bits are written by software to configure the eye or direction mode.
You see the eye using the Y direction here.
Yeah.
So you said the eye or direction mode.
It says when we set the two bit two zero zero, we've set it as input.
When we set it to one zero, we've set it as general-purpose output mode.
When we set it to zero one, we've set it to alternate function mode.
And when we said it to one one, we've said it to unlock mode.
So we have four different modes or directions here.
Right.
So what, um, what we have here.
It's not clearly stated here.
But not one here.
These two bits are useful.
Configuring all this is mode zero.
I should see more zero here.
These two bits, which is bits and bytes, one more zero is useful, configuring all pins, zeros of
every port.
So if I'm dealing with P is zero.
I have to use more zero.
If I'm dealing with please you.
I have to use more to zero.
If I'm dealing with p.c zero point zero p e p h zero or more two in the same way mode five over here.
Whereas Mode five, mode five over here is for or pin pin fives.
So this is the one we're looking for.
We have to set mode five two two one zero.
So what does this mean.
It means we have a 32 bit, 32 bit binary number and that that's pit number ten.
We have to set it to one.
We have to make sure bits number 10 is set to one bits.
Number eleven is set to zero, all the other bits.
We don't care about them.
They deal with other pains.
But specifically, four bits.
Number ten and eleven.
We have to make sure.
We have to make sure they are set to.
Yes, sir.
To bits.
One and zero, as we have over here, if you don't understand, is live in.
Live it in the questions area.
So mode five is for P five.
So what is Mod five.
Would five deals with pit number ten and eleven.
So we set pits number ten to one.
And then bitz number eleven to zero.
By doing this we'll set it to general purpose output mode and output mode is what would output our L.E.
delight.
So let's take some note.
I'll come over here.
Set.
Bit ten to one.
And bit eleven to zero in GPL.
You a
mode register.
And this will give us output mode.
OK.
So after this we would have this set us output mode.
Now how do we write to the GPL Open?
Remember we said there are at least two registers you have to deal with.
There is the direction register and the data register.
Well, yeah.
The data register allows us to get the data.
I get it or give it based on whether we've configured for input or output.
So when we turn on the ality, when we want to turn it off to how do we do the on and off to do this,
we would have to access the data register.
And just like the direction register, silicon manufacturers give this register different names also.
So in some data sheet or reference modules, you find it's called the data register.
In others you'd find not data register, but a name is still descriptive of its function.
So over here, it is called the Output Data Register.
Over here, they've broken the data register into inputs, data register and output data register such
that when you are dealing with GPA, you set as an input.
You use the input data register.
And when you are dealing with it as an output, you use the output data register.
So let's find the output data register and see what it presents to us.
When I come up here and then I'll do a control f and then our search o t r does what it is called or
hit enter and it brings me over here.
GPL, you put output data register.
Click this over here.
And this explains what we've got.
You can close this.
So it says what does it say.
It says GPA.
You put the data register.
No problem.
And over here we have only r y meaning Y is from zero through fifteen.
The top is reserved.
So we have output data.
Register.
What is your one, two, three.
And these correspond to the PIN numbers.
So if we are dealing with PIN five, then this is where our output is going to be.
We are going to write our output here.
We're going to write one, two bits, number five over here.
And by writing one, two bits, number five, ten P a five is going to be set high.
It's going to be set to own.
It's going to be set to one, whichever you prefer.
So
we take note.
Right.
I'll see.
One, right, one, two GP, are you a GP, are you a.
Oh, dear.
Bit five.
To set P a five on and write zero.
I'm just put in this here for your revision, right.
Zero to set it off.
Right.
So we have everything we need.
And then, um, we can, um, we can, um, conclude here and continue the next lesson we've recorded
over, I think, 30 minutes.
So he's getting a bit long.
You can, um, stretch stretch your fingers.
I had my my university professor once told me, you know, when you move your fingers, when you move
your your joints, when you move them, especially the little joints rapidly, it keeps you awake.
So every now and then in class, he makes us stand up and then, you know, flex our fingers and then
take off our shoes and flex our toes.
You can imagine.
Apparently keeps people awake.
So you can use this break to do that.
And I'll see you in the next lesson.